Héctor Climente González

Machine Learning researcher

Paris, France
+33 7 68 13 20 39
https://hclimente.eu
https://github.com/hclimente

ABOUT ME

"Learn only to be content" – Inscription in Ryōan-ji, Kyōto.

The driving forces of my life are learning and personal growth. I strongly believe in multidisciplinarity and collaboration, and created synergies by combining engineering and basic research, biology and machine learning, academia and private sector.

SELECTED WORK EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral researcher

MAY 2020 - NOW

RIKEN AIP

▶ Development of feature selection methods for ultra-high dimensional datasets, with emphasis on network regularization and interaction detection.

Doctoral researcher

OCT 2016 - APR 2020

Institut Curie & Mines Paris Tech

- ▶ Development of feature selection methods for ultra-high dimensional datasets, with emphasis on biological networks.
- ▶ Application of the aforementioned methods to biomarker discovery in GWAS datasets, both single-SNP and epistasis.
- ▶ R package *martini* published in Bioconductor, and Python package *spada* in PyPI.
- ▶ Conducted internships in Liège University and RIKEN AIP.

Research assistant

DEC 2013 - AUG 2016

Pompeu Fabra University

- ▶ Large-scale analysis of the involvement of alternative splicing in cancer
- ▶ Statistical interaction detection using mutual exclusion.

Head of Biocomputing

SEP 2014 - MAY 2015

Anaxomics Biotech Ltd.

- ▶ Responsible for the development and maintenance of pipelines for the statistical treatment of omics data.
- ▶ Collaboration with IT and Data analysis departments regarding database, software and infrastructure maintenance, and product deployment.

EDUCATION

2016 – 2020 **Ph.D. in Bioinformatics**

Paris Sciences & Lettres Univ.

2012 – 2014 M.Sc. in Bioinformatics

GPA 9/IO

Pompeu Fabra University

2010 – 2013 **B.Sc. in Biochemistry**

GPA 8.74/10, 1st Class Honors *Barcelona Autonomous Univ.*

2008 – 2012 B.Sc. in Biotechnology

GPA 8.58/10

Barcelona Autonomous Univ.

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Co-author of 10 articles, cited over 300 times.

Climente-González et al. (2020). Comparing and combining network methods to understand the genetics of familial breast cancer susceptibility *BiorXiv*

Climente-González et al. (2019). Block HSIC Lasso: model-free biomarker detection for ultra-high dimensional data. *Bioinformatics*, 35 (15), i427–i435.

Climente-González et al. (2017). The functional impact of alternative splicing in cancer. Cell reports, 20 (9), 2215-2226.

SELECTED AWARDS

2020 Special Postdoc. Researcher

RIKEN

2016 – 2019 **PhD EU Fellowship**

MSCA COFUND

LANGUAGES

SPANISH Native

ENGLISH Fluent

FRENCH Intermediate

JAPANESE Beginner

TECHNICAL SKILLS

PROGRAMMING Python, R, C++, Bash

PYTHON networkx, numpy, pandas, scikit-learn

r tidyverse, igraph, Rcpp

BIG DATA nextflow, HPC (PBS Torque, Slurm),

SQL, Jupyter

OMICS GWAS, RNA-Seq (single cell and bulk),

MS-MS proteomics

ML/STATISTICS Graph regularization, kernels,

statistical interaction, nonlinear association, selection inference,

deep learning

DEVOPS Docker, conda, unit testing, continuous

integration, git

SOFT SKILLS

- ▶ Experienced **communicator**: talks in international conferences, lead writer of articles and grant proposals, imparted workshops on reproducible research.
- ▶ **Project management** in teams and singleperson projects, **mentoring**, and coordinating **international collaborations**.
- ▶ **Organization** of summer school on breast cancer, **teaching** assistant in large scale machine learning course.
- Courses on critical thinking, ethics, project management, theater, and mindfulness.